This podcast is sponsored by Stay Calm, a new book by David Booth. If you like the psychology of money, I think you'll like Stay Calm. I've been reading it and a lot of what David shares really resonates with how I think about money and investing. The importance of time in the market versus timing the market, the power of human ingenuity, and learning how to manage uncertainty. David distills 50 years of insights from a successful investing career. He worked on the first index funds, he founded dimensional fund advisors, and the University of Chicago Business School is named after him.
I've read a ton of financial books. Many of them feel complicated. This is not one of those. The writing is clear. The lessons are clear. There's a lot of great stories. It's a practical book that can help you feel calmer and more confident about investing. For more information, visit StayComInvesting.com. I started as a finance writer in 2008. And one of the big stories of that year in the economy besides the housing crisis and the financial crisis was that the federal government breached $10 trillion of debt.
Federal debt, that's how much debt the government was in, huge story at the time, a big, scary round number that would have been completely insane eight years before when the government was running a surplus during that period, $10 trillion, how could we ever manage that? It seems so quaint to say that now because last week, one of the big economic news stories that was everywhere on every publication, financial news, non-financial news, it was everywhere, is that the federal government just passed $40 trillion of debt.
And on one hand, it's insane as a share of GDP, which is the way that you want to measure how much debt we're in. This chart shows federal debt as a share of GDP. And you can see now it's higher today than it was just after World War II, which is unbelievable because we're not in a world war right now. And we had COVID, we had the financial crisis, but a relatively strong economy to have this much debt without any kind of immediate crises feels insane. $40 trillion in debt.
I want to add a little bit of context to this without minimizing it because it is a big issue. The government will spend over a trillion dollars on interest payments this year, which is more than we spend on defense. It's a huge issue. That's a lot of money any way you spend it. I don't want to minimize any of this, but I want to put a little context around this. Over the last 20 years, the federal government has gone into ever increasing amounts of debt, even as a share of GDP. It's gone up and up and up. That's what the last chart showed. Something else happened at the same time. That was very important.
and almost completely ignored. Because we love bad news more than we love good news. I have almost never seen this chart or this topic discussed in a major news outlet. At the same time, the federal government was going into more debt. Households and corporations and the private sector of the economy was shedding debt relative to its income. This chart that I want to show you is household debt across America as a share of household income. And as you can see,
It has declined every year since 2008 and it is the lowest by far that it has been in more than 20 years. Household debt as a share of GDP has gone from about 100% to less than 70%. We have shed 30% of household debt relative to GDP over the last 20 years. That's a very big deal. Now part of this, the reason that household debt to GDP has gone down so much,
is because young people in particular can't afford homes, which means they don't have mortgages relative to what they would have in previous generations. So this is not all explicitly good news that you might think, but it happened. Household debt to GDP has gone down. And yes, interest rates have gone up a little bit, but even when you look at household debt payments, as this chart shows here, it's about the lowest that it's been in more than 20 years, and it's gone down a lot.
Now, I want to bring this back to the conversation about $40 trillion of government debt because the financial system is one big machine. It's one system. And it doesn't make a ton of sense all the time to the segregate one part of that system and say, look how much debt the government's in. Or if this was 20 years ago, look how much debt households are in. It's one big system that is financing all of this. And so this next chart that I'm going to show you, this chart is all debt throughout the economy. Federal debt, household debt,
government debt, state debt, municipal debt, every bit of debt throughout the economy as a share of GDP. And it is about flat over the last 20 years, and down fairly considerably from where it was in 2008. Because what has happened is when the federal government went into a lot of debt, households were shedding it at the same time in about the same amounts. And so the total amount throughout the system as a share of the economy is about flat.
Now, does that mean there's nothing to worry about? No, of course not. Because just as in 2008, when households had a ton of debt, you reach a crisis where that segment of the economy gets into trouble. Now, governments, particularly the federal government, doesn't necessarily have any issue with repaying its debt. It deals with debt in a different way, which is inflation. That's frankly what we did in the 1970s, and it'll probably be how we deal with this going forward. But when you look at the full system,
And you ask the question, how could we possibly be able to add $40 trillion in debt without there being seemingly a huge financial crisis due to it, which would have seemed insane in 2008. I think this is the answer. Governments are more indebted than ever. Households are the least indebted that they have been in decades. And you put those two things together and that's where we are. All right. Let me get into some of your questions. First question is from Ken. He says,
You've mentioned in your book and an interview that smart and knowledgeable people get themselves into trouble with money. What are some areas of life that smart, knowledgeable people get themselves into trouble? I love this topic because I think money is one of the few areas in life where I think the correlation between your intelligence and your outcome is not very strong. And sometimes it can actually be the other way around. I've often thought there is a sweet spot with money and intelligence where you want to be smart enough to understand the basics.
But you don't want to be so smart that the basics bore you because when the basics bore you You have to just to remain like stimulated and excited You have to jump into a different level of complexity and that's where some of the biggest mistakes are made often what happens with very smart people is what you might call intelligence creep Where if you are very intelligent in one aspect of life you assume that that intelligence should spill over to another aspect of your life
And so, an example, if you are a doctor or an engineer, you know you're very smart, you know you have a high IQ, and therefore, if you're a very talented brain surgeon, it's an easy step to make to say, I should be able to pick stocks. I'm a brain surgeon. How hard could it be? Those are the people who really get themselves into trouble is when you have the assumption that you don't know where the boundaries of your intelligence are. That's a big deal. Another that happens a lot are people who are very credentialed.
with their academics or their work credentials, whatever it might be, discount the points of views of people who are not as credentialed. And so how many times has a company hired a very smart PhD consultant to solve a problem that the blue collar workers on the factory line knew how to solve themselves, but management didn't want to take their views seriously because they weren't as credentialed. I think that happens all the time. One other area that happens a lot is the realization that in school,
the competitor is the test. It's you versus the test. But in the real world, it is you versus your boss, your employees, your customers, your shareholders, regulators. There's like so many different conflicting people that you're competing with that it's a very different game. And all of those people need to be persuaded. And sometimes they are persuaded by more than just having the right answer. At school, if you have the right answer, it's done. You've won. In the real world, you could have the right answer for your customers.
But it's not the right answer for shareholders. It's not the right answer for regulators. And so it's just a much more complex game that very smart people who do exceptionally well in one aspect of life tend not to do that well in other areas in life. Now, look, if you look at the correlation between people who went to Harvard and how much money they make, there is a correlation there. People who go to Harvard, on average, make more money than people who went to lower state schools. That's obvious. But there are so many successful entrepreneurs, successful workers, successful, however you want to measure it.
who did not get very high SAT scores, who didn't go to the best schools, who are not the standout students, but they have a lot of street smarts, they have a lot of integrity, they know what they want to do, and they can live a wonderful life just being that. Those have always been the people who I look up to. Our next question from Kevin. He says, an anecdote told about Joseph Kennedy claims that when the shoe shine boy is giving you stock tips, it's time to get out.
What are your thoughts on the proliferation of retail investors, individual investors? Do you think that they are skewing the market or are the dollar amounts so small in relation to big institutional investors that they have very little, if any, effect on prices? Here's one thing that I think about that is an amazing stat, I think. In 1929, at the peak of the 1920s boom and that stock market bubble that preceded the Great Depression, 5% of Americans own stocks. That's it. There's a very small percentage of people who are participating in the stock market. Today, it is over 55%.
of Americans own stocks. The vast majority of them in their retirement accounts, therefore 01Ks. Now it's very common these days to look to think about retail investors and the volatility because they are known for things like meme stocks and pushing up, you know, game stocks and Hertz and all these other crazy stocks that went to the moon for no seeming reason and then crash back down and to look at all the chaos and volatility being caused by retail investors, many of whom are literally 19 year olds trading in the Robin Hood accounts.
That is so minuscule relative to the pool of all investors. So I pulled up a little bit of data here Vanguard the big index fund low-cost investing house has over 13 trillion dollars of assets Robin Hood the account the place where young people go and trade and retail investors tend to hang out is about 350 billion
And so Vanguard is more than 30 times the size of Robinhood. It is so much that in July, Vanguard brought in more than $50 billion, or Robinhood brought in about five. And so the amount of money going into low-cost, basic, boring index funds is in order of magnitude more than the amount of money that is going to trade crazy day trading, penny stocks, whatever it might be. Now, one thing that's important in terms of how markets have changed over time.
is when you realize that 55% of Americans own stocks and the vast majority of them are dollar cost averaging into an index fund in their 401k, where they lost the password, they don't even know how to log into their account, it just happens automatically every paycheck. That is a big deal because that can be hundreds of billions of dollars every year that buys regardless of what's going on in the world. Economies doing great, they buy. Economies doing poorly, they buy. Stock market crashes, they buy every single week.
And that is a pretty new development in the history of the stock market. It used to be not that long ago, 20 or 30 years ago. Remember, the Roth IRA was opened and became a thing in 1998. These are relatively new phenomenons. It used to be that everyone bought and sold stocks based off of their insight or their hunch. You bought when you thought a stock was going to go up and you sold when you thought it was going to go down. For every single transaction, that's effectively what it was.
And today the vast majority of what's going on is not that whatsoever. It's this, as Josh Brown once put it, the relentless bid of constant buying. Now that doesn't mean that markets will go up straight forever. We've seen during this era plenty of stocks can fall 50%, 80%, 90%.
doesn't necessarily matter. There's still a lot of price discovery of stocks eventually hitting their true value and finding that spot. But if you want to talk about the chaos of retail investors and day traders, I think it is so minuscule relative to the tsunami of people who dollar cost average into index funds, like myself, by the way, that is a much bigger thing. And if you made the argument that markets will be more relatively stable because of that,
than they were 50 or 100 years ago. I would believe that. Not stable, but more stable than they were 50 or 100 years ago. I would actually buy that argument because there was so much money that buys regardless of what's going on in the world. All right, next question. You write a lot about luck and risk being siblings. How do you stay humble about your own success while still taking credit where it's due? This is a very challenging one because it's very often for anyone's life or career,
that you want to take credit for the things that did well, and you want to blame others for the things that didn't go so well. I think the best way to think about it is what is repeatable? What about my life could I repeat again? What about your life could you repeat again? Versus the things that happen to be a certain time and a place that you could not repeat. I remember many years ago, a colleague interviewed Alice Schroeder who was Warren Buffett's biographer. She wrote the book, The Snowball, kind of the biggest biography about Warren Buffett. And someone asked her, they said,
If Warren Buffett were born 30 or 50 years later, would he have had the success that he did? Without hesitation, she said, absolutely not. Like, yes, he's a genius at thinking about businesses and investing, and he's still doing great at it, but so much of his success was a time and a place of the skills that he had were so applicable to the 1950s, 60s, and 70s, which is when the bulk of his money was actually made in relative terms. And so you can look at someone like Buffett as I would and say, what can I learn from him?
his patience, his ability to compound over decades, those are all things you can learn from him. I cannot, you cannot replicate the time period that he lived in. And that's true for my life, it's true for your life. It's always just been, what can you repeat? A good way to separate luck from skill, this was an idea from Michael Mobusen was, can you fail intentionally? And so,
If I were to buy lottery tickets, I could not fail intentionally. There's a chance that I might win. But if I were shooting free throws, I could fail intentionally. I could miss every single one of them. And so shooting basketball is more skill than luck. There are other endeavors like buying stocks maybe, where you can win without trying. Or you can win even if you're trying not to win. And so I think that's a good framework for how to separate luck versus skill. All right, last question.
How do you separate signal from noise given how much financial content is produced daily, including my own? I've always had this idea that you really need to go out of your way to define what game you're playing in finance, because there's a million different games that you can play. You can try to maximize your wealth early on and earn the highest investing returns every year. You could not care about any of that and just say, I'm perfectly happy earning mediocre returns and living a mediocre life and spending my time growing flowers and going for walks, whatever it may be.
there's a million different games that you can play. And we do a lot of damage to ourselves in the financial media when it is proposed as there is one right way to play. And so if you're to watch CNBC or read a lot of financial content, it is almost never explained as if you are a day trader, you should short Microsoft. It's almost always explained as you should short Microsoft without any context over who that advice might be relevant for. And so I think the way that I like to separate noise
for my own life signal from noise is I have a very clear idea of what game I'm trying to play financially in investing and with savings and with lifestyle. And it makes it very easy that when you come across a piece of content to instantly recognize that that's not relevant for me. And so every day I read the Wall Street Journal, Bloomberg Financial Times, The Economist, and it's skimming that and realizing, oh, that headline looks very interesting and might be relevant to me. I might learn something applicable to my life.
from that headline. That next headline means nothing to me whatsoever. Well, it would never occur to me that that would be relevant information to me, even if it's relevant to you if you're playing a different game. And so going out of your way to define the game that you're playing is probably the most important part of separating signal from noise in the financial media. All right, I want to recommend something for you now. This book by Yoni Applebaum called Stuck is fantastic. And it is a very clear explanation, historical explanation.
for why people are stuck and by stuck he means that for most of American history most Americans moved and they moved often they would live in a house for a year or two and then they'd move they move up they move across town they move to different towns and Relative to what we used to do. We don't do that anymore and how much of economic dynamism is Reliant on people moving and if people are stuck in their town or in their house it slows a lot of things down and one of the biggest reasons
that people are stuck is because of housing prices. Housing prices go up and up and up and young people can't afford them. They can't afford to buy a house. They get stuck in the house because they have a low interest rate mortgage that they can't move from. And it slows everything down. And it's a very clear explanation about why we stopped building so many homes, the homes that we need. And when home construction went down, home prices went up. And when home prices went up, people got stuck. When people get stuck,
the economy tends to slow down. If you're into economic history and things like that, it's fantastic. That's it for this week. We'll see you next time.
The Home Depot has the tools you need to check projects off your list. Shop Labor Day savings at the Home Depot and gear up for fall projects with the right tools to keep your projects moving. Have no fear, Chosen Foods is here to defend your favorite foods from the forces of seedy oils and sketchy ingredients. With cooking oils, salad dressings and mayo all powered by the good fats from 100% pure avocado oil and simple delicious ingredients. Chosen Foods.